Guide to the Knut Schmidt-Nielsen Papers, 1939-1994 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Knut Schmidt-Nielsen papers 1939-1994 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Schmidt-Nielsen, Knut
18 linear feet Extent: 13,500 Items
Biologist whose main area of research was in animal physiology, particularly that of the camel. Schmidt-Nielsen spent the bulk of his career at Duke University, from 1952 to 1995, during which he published approximately 300 articles, and key works such as Animal Physiology, and Scaling: Why Is Animal Size So Important? Collection contains correspondence, research notes, field data, published materials, lecture notes, memos, reports, grant applications, and other materials. The papers span the years 1939-1994, documenting Schmidt-Nielsen's active research and teaching careers.
RL.01148
Language: Material in English, Norwegian, and German
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Knut Schmidt-Nielsen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1994, 2001, and 2006.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1915 Sept. 15 Born in Trondheim, Norway
1933-1937 Attended University of Oslo
1946 Received D.Phil. from University of Copenhagen
1949-1952 Assistant professor at University of Cincinnati
1952 Became a United States citizen
1952-1995 Professor at Duke University
1953 Awarded Guggenheim fellowship
1970 Published Animal Physiology
1984 Published Scaling: Why Is Animal Size So Important?
2007 Jan. 25 Died in Durham, North Carolina
Collection Overview
The Knut Schmidt-Nielsen Papers span the years 1939-1994, documenting the life and work of this prominent animal physiologist and educator. Formats include correspondence, research notes, field data, published material, lectures, memos, reports, grant applications, and other materials. Schmidt-Nielsen spent most of his career at Duke University where he served on faculty from 1952 to 1995, studying comparative animal physiology and environmental conditions in the desert, particularly in the Sahara and North Africa, with a particular interest in the camel. In addition, Schmidt-Nielsen was active as a lecturer and as a member of various biological organizations, including the International Union of Physiological Sciences and the Interunion Commission on Comparative Physiology, as well as being heavily involved with the publication of News in Physiological Sciences. Also documented is Schmidt-Nielsen's active role as teacher and advisor, and his involvement in the Duke University Nixon Library Committee. The collection is divided into the following series: Animal Physiology Research, Correspondence, Engagements, Graduate Student, International Union of Physiological Sciences, News in Physiological Sciences, Publications, and Subject Files.
The Animal Physiology Research Notes Series contains materials from Schmidt-Nielsen's research trip to the Sahara in 1953 and 1954, including correspondence, data, and journal entries. The Correspondence Series is by far the largest in the collection, and contains both official professional correspondence as well as scientific discussions and other related material. Much of the early correspondence is in Norwegian. The Engagements Series documents lectures given by Schmidt-Nielsen from throughout his career, including lecture notes, slides, and diagrams. Schmidt-Nielsen's teaching work is documented in the Graduate Student Series, chiefly his interactions with graduate student advisees. The International Union of Physiological Sciences Series houses materials from Schmidt-Nielsen's involvement with this organization, of which he was president from 1980 to 1986. The series includes minutes, memos, reports, correspondence, and other related materials. The News in Physiological Sciences Series consists of material related to the publication of this journal. In the Publications Series, there are copies of nearly every article Schmidt-Nielsen published. The Subject Files Series contains miscellaneous material grouped by subject regarding organizations, grant applications, and topics in animal research. Another small series, the Translations Series houses 33 published translations of a selection of Schmidt-Nielsen's textbooks. Finally, the Audiovisual Series houses three sound recordings of conference talks given by Schmidt-Nielsen during the 1960s. Original recordings are closed to use; please contact Research Services staff concerning access.
Unprocessed addition (2006-0026) (11,468 items, 18 lin. ft.; dated 1902-2003) comprises personal and professional correspondence, subject and genealogy files, lecture notes, calendars, clippings, and photographs. The addition is not represented in the finding aid, but a preliminary inventory is available on request. For research access, please contact the Research Services staff.
Subject Headings
Animal mechanics; Camels; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Nixon Library Committee; Duke University. Zoology Dept; International Union of Physiological Sciences; Interunion Commission on Comparative Physiology; News in Physiological Sciences; Northern Africa -- Environmental conditions; Sahara -- Environmental conditions; Physiologists -- United States; Physiology -- Study and teaching (Higher); Physiology, Comparative; Schmidt-Nielsen, Knut, 1915-; Zoologists -- Correspondence; Sound recordings
Detailed Description of Collection
- Animal Physiology Research Series, 1952-1956, (1 box)
  Contains folders of correspondence, data, and other supporting documents related to Schmidt-Nielsen's research on desert animals in the Sahara between August 1953 and July 1954. The folders are divided into two groups, general information and data, and are arranged alphabetically within the groups. His personal correspondence and journal entries are available in a bound format within the series. The data folders contain experiment results and research notes on camels, donkeys, rodents, and plants.
  - Animal studies--general, 1952-1954, (15 folders) (Box 1)
  - Animal studies--data, 1953-1956, (16 folders) (Box 1)
- Awards and Diplomas Series, 1947-1990, (1 folder)
  - Diplomas, awards, and honors (Opaperfolder 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1939-1985 and undated, (16 boxes)
  Includes scientific inquiries and invitations; professional correspondence with colleagues, researchers, publishers, and graduate students; and letters of recommendation. Interspersed in the series are vitae and statements of plans, grant application materials, copyright releases, requests for plant and animal samples, occasional newpaper clippings, photographs, and postcards. The 1948-1952 correspondence with the Office of Naval Research contains grant application files. Correspondence from Schmidt-Nielsen's stay in Algeria in 1953-1954 documents logistics and field work during the trip. Duke University correspondence includes records of departmental procedures, graduate students documentation, and requests for lab equipment. An extensive portion of the early correspondence is in Norwegian; occasional documents are in French, German, or Spanish. The folders are labelled and arranged alphabetically by last name or subject. Additional professional correspondence can be found in other series, particularly the International Union of Physiological Sciences and the News in Physiological Sciences Series.
  - 1939, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - 1946-1947, (9 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1948-1952
    - A-O, (39 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1948-1952 (Box 3)
    - O-Z, (22 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1952-1953, (50 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - A-T, (36 folders) (Box 4)
    - Trip to Algeria, (12 folders) (Box 4)
    - T-Z, (7 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1955-1960
    - A, (1 folder) (Box 4)
  - 1955-1960 (Box 5)
    - A-D, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Duke University, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - E-R, (27 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1955-1960 (Box 6)
    - R-Z, (15 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1960-1964
    - A-D, (22 folders) (Box 6)
    - Duke University, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - E-G, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 7)
    - H-Z, (37 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1964-1968 (Box 8)
    - A-D, (27 folders) (Box 8)
    - Duke University, (14 folders) (Box 8)
    - E-G, (7 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1964-1968 (Box 9)
    - H-S, (34 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1964-1968 (Box 10)
    - S, (7 folders) (Box 10)
    - South Africa, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - S-Z, (13 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1968-1973
    - A-C, (11 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1968-1973 (Box 11)
    - D, (6 folders) (Box 11)
    - Duke University, (12 folders) (Box 11)
    - D-L, (36 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1968-1973 (Box 12)
    - M-Z, (48 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1974-1979 (Box 13)
    - A-H, (35 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1974-1979 (Box 14)
    - H-S, (37 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1974-1979 (Box 15)
    - S-Z, (19 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1979-1985
    - A-D, (21 fodlers) (Box 15)
    - Duke University, (9 folders) (Box 15)
    - D-E, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1979-1985 (Box 16)
    - F-N, (40 folders) (Box 16)
    - National Academy of Sciences, (5 folders) (Box 16)
    - O-S, (14 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1979-1985 (Box 17)
    - S-Z, (15 folders) (Box 17)
- Engagements Series, 1948-1994, (3 boxes)
  Contains records of Schmidt-Nielsen's participation in scientific meetings and conferences, as well as individual lectures and presentations. A large part of the series is comprised of Schmidt-Nielsen's lecture notes, diagrams, and slides; complete drafts of presentations are less common. Subjects of the lectures include: physiology and adaptations of desert animals; breathing and locomotion; and scaling and size in biology. Also included are conference-related materials, such as correspondence, brochures, and posters. Extensive material is available for the conference on Scaling in Biology held at Duke University in 1973. Interspersed through the series are records from the annual International Conference on Comparative Physiology. A few documents are in French, German, Japanese, and Norwegian. Folders are labelled by date of event and topic, and are arranged chronologically by month of the year. A separate folder at the end of the series contains a complete chronological list of lectures given by Schmidt-Nielsen.
  - 1948-1963, (43 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1963-1973, (48 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1973-1980, (61 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1980-1989, (56 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1989-1994, (30 folders) (Box 21)
- Graduate Student Series, 1953-1986 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Documents Schmidt-Nielsen's role as an instructor and mentor to graduate students. The series contains personal and official correspondence, application files, and letters of recommendation. The student files often include research proposals, proposals for programs of graduate, tutorials, exams, and other written work submitted by students, with comments from Schmidt-Nielsen. Interspersed are funding files and financial documents. Folders are arranged alphabetically by last name of student. Note: materials are open for use, but are covered by privacy and confidentiality agreement which must be signed by researchers.
  - A-B, (7 folders) (Box 21)
  - C-P, (24 folders) (Box 22)
  - P-R, (13 folders) (Box 23)
- International Union of Physiological Sciences Series, 1953-1986, bulk 1980-1986, and undated, (7 boxes)
  Consists of materials and correspondence pertaining to the administrative organization and activities of the International Union of Physiological Sciences (IUPS), divided into three subseries: General Information, Meeting Notes, and Correspondence. The General Information Subseries pertains to the period during which Schmidt-Nielsen served as President of IUPS, from 1980 to 1986, and includes meeting minutes, membership lists, memos, reports, and speeches, arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within topics. The Meeting Notes Subseries detail the planning and arrangements for international congresses and include programs, lists of participants, and presentation titles; the subseries is arranged by year of event. The Correspondence Subseries includes individual correspondence and memos related to different activities of IUPS and is arranged alphabetically. This series also contains some material in German, French, and Japanese.
  - General Information Subseries, 1953-1986, bulk 1975-1985, and undated (Box 23)
    - Commissions, 1980, 1983-1985 (Box 23)
    - Congress notes, 1977-1986, (7 folders) (Box 23)
    - Constitution, 1980, 1985 (Box 23)
    - Committee on Space Research, 1982, 1984 (Box 23)
    - Council notes, 1953-1983, bulk 1980-1983, (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - Council notes, 1980-1986, (10 folders) (Box 24)
    - (Box 24)
    - Educational programs, 1980, 1984 (Box 24)
    - (Box 24)
    - Executive Committee meetings, 1980-1985, (8 folders) (Box 24)
    - Expenses and finances, 1980-1985, (5 folders) (Box 24)
    - Interunion Commission, 1975-1985, (19 folders) (Box 24)
    - International Union of Biological Sciences (IUBS), 1976-1981, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - International Union for Pure and Applied Biophysics (IUPAB), 1978-1980 (Box 24)
    - IUPS Council members, 1974-1982, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - IUPS Council members, 1976-1981, (13 folders) (Box 25)
    - Newsletter, 1978 May (Box 25)
    - News in Physiological Sciences Proposal, 1983-1984 (Box 25)
    - Nominating Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 25)
    - US National Committee for IUPS, 1975 (Box 25)
  - Meeting Notes Subseries, 1961-1986, bulk 1972-1983, and undated
    - Assorted meeting notes, 1961, 1964-1971, 1977 (Box 25)
    - 1972, Italy, (4 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1974, Switzerland, (12 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1976, Switzerland - 1976, (6 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1978, Switzerland, (15 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1980, Denmark (Box 26)
    - 1983, Sidney, (30 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1986, Vancouver (Box 26)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1977-1990, and undated
    - A, (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - A-K, (33 folders) (Box 27)
    - K-S, (21 folders) (Box 28)
    - S-Z, (19 folders) (Box 29)
- News in Physiological Sciences Series, 1979-1990 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Contains materials related to Schmidt-Nielsen's work with News in Physiological Sciences, including correspondence between Schmidt-Nielsen and editors, authors, and publishers; administrative documents; notes, manuscripts, corrected drafts, and occasional published articles. Folders arranged alphabetically by subject title.
  - Advertisments, 1986, and undated (Box 29)
  - Agreement, 1983-1985 (Box 29)
  - Articles, suggestions, 1986 (Box 29)
  - APS archives, 1986-1990 (Box 29)
  - Authors, 1985-1986 (Box 29)
  - Budget, 1985-1986 (Box 29)
  - Cambridge University Press, 1983 (Box 29)
  - Complimentary copies, 1985 (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1990, (42 folders) (Box 30)
  - Editorial work, 1982-1988, (11 folders) (Box 31)
  - Final report, 1988 (Box 31)
  - Guidelines for authors, 1986 (Box 31)
  - IUPS commission chairmen, 1984 (Box 31)
  - Launching committee correspondence, 1984 (Box 31)
  - Letters, 1986-1988, (3 folders) (Box 31)
  - Lists of board members and editors, 1986-1987 (Box 31)
  - Managing board, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Manuscript for Nobel - The Award of the Prize, 1987 (Box 31)
  - Meeting notes, 1984, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Memos, 1986, 1988, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Name, cover page, contents, undated (Box 31)
  - Photocopies, 1986, 1988 (Box 31)
  - Preliminary discussion notes, 1983 (Box 31)
  - Publication, 1979-1981 (Box 31)
- Publications Series, 1936-1986, (2 boxes)
  Consists of articles published by Schmidt-Nielsen throughout his career, and includes a full publication list at the beginning of the series. Each article is presented in its final published form, either as a reprint or a full journal, with no notes, manuscripts, proofs, or revisions. Some articles are in German and Danish. Folders are labeled and arranged chronologically by year.
  - 1936-1959, (4 folders) (Box 31)
  - 1960-1986, (6 folders) (Box 32)
- Subject Files Series, 1952-1991 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Contains miscellaneous materials on a variety of individual subjects related to Schmidt-Nielsen. The bulk of material consists of funding inquiries, grant applications, and reports pertaining to different organizations. The series also contains material about scholarly societies and their activities, interspersed with correspondence. A small section includes documents on animal experiments. Folders are labeled by subject and arranged alphabetically within subjects.
  - American Physiological Society (APS), 1956, 1962-1987, (13 folders) (Box 32)
  - American Society of Zoologists (ASZ), 1961-1991, (folder 1 of 6) (Box 32)
  - American Society of Zoologists (ASZ), 1961-1991, (folders 2-6 of 6) (Box 33)
  - Animal experimentation, 1980-1987, (7 folders) (Box 33)
  - Antarctica, 1972-1974, (4 folders) (Box 33)
  - Australia camel research, 1979-1983, (5 folders) (Box 33)
  - Grant applications, 1969-1987, (folders 1-10 of 24) (Box 33)
  - Grant applications, 1969-1987, (folders 11-24 of 24) (Box 34)
  - International communication, 1980-1987, (10 folders) (Box 34)
  - James Jones NIH grant, 1977-1978, 1985, (3 folders) (Box 34)
  - National Geographic Society, 1969-1971, 1976-1980, (10 folders) (Box 34)
  - NIH grants, 1962-1970, (8 folders) (Box 34)
  - NIH grants, 1952-1987, and undated, (8 folders) (Box 35)
  - NSF grant, 1958-1966, 1977-1981, (6 folders) (Box 35)
  - Nixon Library, 1980-1981, (10 folders) (Box 35)
  - Old grants, 1953-1969, (16 folders) (Box 36)
  - Other grants, 1961-1984, (7 folders) (Box 36)
  - Travel, 1960-1962, (2 folders) (Box 36)
- Translations Series, 1961-1991, (4 boxes)
  Addition 2001-0075 houses about 50 published translations of Schmidt-Nielsen’s textbooks. Titles include Animal Physiology; Scaling: Why Is Animal Size So Important; and How Animals Work. Languages include Japanese, Polish, Russian, German, Greek, Spanish, French, German, Italian, Hindi, Malay, Norwegian, Hebrew, Swedish, and Portuguese.
  - 19 books, 2 folders (Box 38)
  - 10 books, 2 folders (Box 39)
  - 3 books (Box 40)
  - 17 books (Box 41)
  - 11 books (Box 42)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1967-1969, (1 box)
  Houses three sound recordings on 7" reel-to-reel tape, of Schmidt-Nielsen giving lectures at two conferences: the Symposium on Comparative Animal Physiology, Washington, January 1967 (title is "The Unusual Animal, or to Expect the Unexpected"); and the Kleiber Symposium held in Davis, California in August 1969 (two reels). Other individuals named on the containers are A. C. Black and Dr. Shannon.
  [Originals closed to use. Technical Services staff must arrange to have use copies made. Please contact Research Services staff before coming to use the collection.]
  - OR1. 1967 Jan., Symposium on Comparative Pharmacology (Box 37)
  - OR2. 1969 Aug., Kleiber Symposium, reel one (Box 37)
  - OR3. 1969 Aug., Kleiber Symposium, reel two (Box 37)